<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for liberty to transport spices vngarbled.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc. 1649.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1045A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1060_69</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208778</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867700</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867700</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120022</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82392)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120022)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 157:E1060[69])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for liberty to transport spices vngarbled.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc. 1649.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Iohn Field for Edward Husband, printer to the Parliament of England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Octob. 13. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The last word of first line of text: 'Parlia-'; first word of line below initial: 'thereby'; the last word of last full line of text: 'upon'.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of a through-paged folio set with a table for the entire set added.</note>
                  <note>Ornament above caption. Initial letter. Text partially in black letter.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trade regulation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spices --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:120022:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:120022:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120022:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon of the Commonwealth</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>AN ACT For liberty to Tranſport Spices Vngarbled.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHereas by an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, made the firſt year of King <hi>James,</hi> for prevention of abuſes committed in putting to ſale of corrupt, unclean, and mingled Spices, Drugs, Wares, and other Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes Garbleable; It was thereby for remedy thereof Enacted, that ſundry ſorts of Spices, Drugs, Wares and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, in the ſaid Act mentioned, and brought into <hi>London,</hi> and there ſold and uttered, ſhould be ſufficiently cleanſed and garbled, before the ſame, or any part thereof ſhould be ſold, upon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120022:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
pain of forfeiture of all ſuch Spices, Drugs, Wares and Merchandizes, or the value thereof which ſhould be ſold: And whereas a great part of the Trade of the Merchants of this Nation, Importing and Exporting of Pepper and other Spices, Drugs, Wares and Merchandize, into and out of this Commonwealth, in their courſe and return of Trade, do Import far greater quantities thereof, then are expended and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this Nation; the overplus whereof (if ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead) wil be no advantage, either to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, or to this Commonwealth; and if allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be exported ungarbled, would tend to the great advancement of Trade &amp; Commerce in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, the ſtrengthning and ſecuring of the State by the encreaſe of Navigation, Warlike Ships and able Seamen, and alſo the great augment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Cuſtom and Excize: All which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England</hi> in Parliament aſſembled, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidering, Do think good to Declare, Enact and Ordain, And it is hereby Enacted, Ordained and Declared, That it ſhall and may be lawful, to and for the ſaid Merchants and People of <hi>England,</hi> and every of them, from time to time, and at all times from and after the Eight and twentieth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred forty nine, to Vend, Trade with, and Export out of this Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> into any the parts beyond the Seas, any quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity or quantities of Pepper, Spices, Wares, and Drugs, and Merchandizes ungarbled, which are or ſhall be hereafter by them Imported as aforeſaid, without any ſevering, ſifting, cleanſing, dividing, or garbling of the ſame. And be it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore Enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That the ſaid Merchants and People of <hi>England,</hi> and every of them, may likewiſe from time to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120022:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
time, and at all times hereafter, utter and put to ſale any Pepper or Spices, Drugs, Wares &amp; Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes, which ſhall be ſo ſevered, or that are or ſhall be uncleanſed, undivided, or ungarbled, to any perſon or perſons whatſoever within this Realm, to be Exported to any part or parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſeas; and that all and every perſon and perſons which ſhall ſo buy any Pepper or other Spices, Drugs, Wares or Merchandizes to Tranſport, ſhall and may Tranſport the ſame Pepper or other Spices, Drugs, Wares and Merchandizes, without any ſevering, cleanſing, dividing, or garbling of the ſame, The ſaid Statute, or any thing to the contrary thereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <abbr>Hen</abbr> Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Field</hi> for <hi>Edward Husband,</hi> Printer to the Parliament of <hi>England, Octob.</hi> 13. 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
